3 At half 12 next day Lord Henry Waton strolled from Ken Street over to the
Albany to call on his uncle, Lord fermer a genial if somewhat rough mannered old
bachelor, whom the outside world called selfish because it derived no particular
benefit from him, but who was considered generous by Society as he fed the people
who amused him. His father had been our ambassador at Madrid when Isabella was
young and Prim unthought of, but had retired from the diplomatic service in a
capricious moment of annoyance on not being offered the Embassy at Paris, a
post to which he considered that he was fully entitled by reason of his birth,
his indolence, the good English of his dispatches, and his inordinate passion for
pleasure. The son, who had been his father’s secretary, had resigned along
with his chief, somewhat foolishly as was thought at the time, and on succeeding
some months later to the title, had set himself to the serious study of the
great great aristocratic art of doing absolutely nothing. He had two large tow houses, but
preferred to live in chambers as it was less trouble, and took most of his meals
at his club. He paid some attention to the management of his ceries in the
Midland counties, excusing himself for this taint of industry on the ground
that the one advantage of having coal was that it enabled a gentleman to
afford the decency of burning wood on his own hearth. In politics he was a tor
except when the Tories were in office, during which period he roundly abused
them for being a pack of Radicals. He was a hero to his valet, who
bullied him, and a terror to most of his relations, whom he bullied in
turn. Only England could have produced him, and he always said that the country was going to the
dogs. His principles were out of date, but there was a good deal to be said for his
prejudices. When Lord re entered the room, he found his uncle sitting in a rough
shooting coat smoking a sherut and grumbling over The
Times “Well, Harry,” said the old gentleman, “what brings you out so early? I thought
you dandies never got up till 2: and were not visible till
5 Pure family affection, I assure you, Uncle George. I want to get something out
of you.” “Money, I suppose,” said Lord fermer making a Ry face. “Well, sit down and tell
me all about it. Young people, nowadays, imagine that money is
everything.” “Yes,” murmured Lord Henry, settling his button hole in his coat; “and
when they grow older they know it. But I don’t want money. It is only people who
pay their bills who want that, Uncle George, and I never pay
mine. Credit is the capital of a younger son, and one lives charmingly upon
it. Besides, I always deal with dart Moore's tradesmen, and consequently they
never bother me. What I want is information: not useful information, of course; useless
information.” “Well, I can tell you anything that is in an English Blue Book, Harry,
although those fellows nowadays write a lot of nonsense. When I was in the Diplomatic,
things were much better. But I hear they let them in now by examination. What can
you expect? Examinations, sir, are pure humbug from beginning to end. If a man is
a gentleman, he knows quite enough, and if he is not a gentleman, whatever he knows
is bad for him.” “Mr. Dorian Gray does not belong to Blue Books, Uncle George,” said Lord Henry
languidly. “Mr. Dorian Gray? Who is he?” asked Lord furore knitting his bushy white
eyebrows. “That is what I've come to learn, Uncle George. Or rather, I know who he is.
He is the last Lord kelo's grandson. His mother was a Deo Lady Margaret
Deo I want you to tell me about his mother. What was she like? Whom did she
marry? You have known nearly everybody in your time, so you might have known her
I'm very much interested in Mr. Gray at present. I have only just met
him kelo's grandson!” echoed the old gentleman kelo's grandson! Of course.... I knew his mother
intimately. I believe I was at her christening. She was an extraord
ordinarily beautiful girl, Margaret Deo and made all the men frantic by running
away with a penniless young fellow— —a mere nobody, sir, a subon in a foot
regiment, or something of that kind.
Certainly. I remember the whole thing as if it happened yesterday. The poor chap was killed in a
duel at Spa a few months after the marriage. There was an ugly story about
it. They said Kelo got some rascally adventurer, some Belgian brute, to insult
his son-in-law in public— —paid him, sir, to do it, paid him— —and that
the fellow spitted his man as if he had been a pigeon. The thing was hushed up,
but igad Kelo ate his chop alone at the club for some time afterwards. He brought
his daughter back with him, I was told, and she never spoke to him again. Oh, yes;
it was a bad business. The girl died, too, died within a
year. So she left a son, did she I'd forgotten that.
What sort of boy is he? If he is like his mother, he must be a good-look
chap.” “He is very good-look ascented Lord Henry. “I hope he will fall into proper
hands,” continued the old man. “He should have a pot of money waiting for him if
Kelo did the right thing by him. His mother had money, too. All the Selby
property came to her, through her grandfather. Her grandfather hated Kelo
thought him a mean dog. He was, too.
Came to Madrid once when I was there IAD I was ashamed of him. The Queen used to
ask me about the English noble who was always quarreling with the cabmen about
their Affairs They made quite a story of it. I didn’t dare show my face at Court
for a month. I hope he treated his grandson better than he did the
jarv I don’t know,” answered Lord Henry. “I fancy that the boy will be well off. He
is not of age yet. He has Selby, I know. He told me so.
And his mother was very beautiful?” “Margaret Deo was one of the
lovliest creatures I ever saw, Harry. What on earth induced her to behave as she
did, I never could understand. She could have married anybody she chose.
Carlington was mad after her. She was romantic, though. All the women of that
family were. The men were a poor lot, but aad the women were wonderful. Carlington
went on his knees to her. Told me so himself. She laughed at him, and there
wasn’t a girl in London at the time who
wasn’t after him. And by the way, Harry, talking about silly marriages, what is
this humbug your father tells me about dartmore wanting to marry an American?
Ain’t English girls good enough for him?” “It is rather fashionable to marry
Americans just now, Uncle George.” “I’ll back English women against
the world, Harry,” said Lord furmer striking the table with his fist. “The
betting is on the Americans.” “They don’t last, I am told,” muttered his
uncle. “A long engagement exhausts them, but they are capital at a steeple chase
They take things flying. I don’t think dartmore has a
chance.” “Who are her people?” grumbled the old gentleman. “Has she got any?” Lord Henry
shook his head. “American girls are as clever at concealing their parents, as
English women are at concealing their past,” he said, rising to go. “They are pork Packers I
suppose?” “I hope so, Uncle George, for dartmore sake. I told that pork packing
is the most lucrative profession in America, after
politics.” “Is she pretty?” “She behaves as if she was beautiful. Most American women do.
It is the secret of their charm.” “Why can’t these American women
stay in their own country? They are always telling us that it is the paradise for
women.” “It is. That is the reason why, like Eve, they are so excessively anxious to
get out of it,” said Lord Henry goodbye Uncle George. I shall be
late for lunch, if I stop any longer. Thanks for giving me the
information I wanted. I always like to know everything about my new friends, and
nothing about my old ones.” “Where are you lunching, Harry?” “At
Aunt Agatha’s I've asked myself and Mr.
Gray. He is her latest Protegé Humph! tell your Aunt Agatha, Harry, not to bother me
anymore with her charity appeals I'm sick of them. Why, the good woman thinks
that I have nothing to do but to write checks for her silly
fads.” “All right, Uncle George, I’ll tell her, but it won’t have any effect.
Philanthropic people lose all sense of humanity. It is their distinguishing
characteristic.” The old gentleman growled approvingly and rang the bell for his
servant. Lord Henry passed up the low arcade into Burlington Street and turned
his steps in the direction of Berkeley Square. So that was the story of Dorian Gray’s
parentage. Crudely as it had been told to him, it had yet stirred him by its
suggestion of a strange, almost modern romance. A beautiful woman risking
everything for a mad passion. A few wild weeks of happiness cut short by a
hideous, treacherous crime. Months of voiceless agony, and then a child born in
pain. The mother snatched away by death, the boy left a solitude and the tyranny
of an old and loveless man. Yes; it was an interesting background. It posed the lad,
made him more perfect, as it were. Behind every exquisite thing that existed, there
was something tragic. Worlds had to be in travail, that the meanest flower might
blow.... And how charming he had been at dinner the night before, as with startled
eyes and lips parted in frightened pleasure he had sat opposite to him at
the club, the red candle shade staining to a richer rose the wakening wonders of
his face. Talking to him was like playing upon an exquisite
violin. He answered to every touch and thrill of the bow.... There was something terribly
enthralling in the exercise of influence.
No other activity was like it. To project one’s soul into some gracious form, and
let it t there for a moment; to hear one’s own intellectual views echoed back
to one with all the added music of passion and youth; to convey one’s
temperament into another as though it were a subtle fluid or a strange
perfume: there was a real joy in that— —perhaps the most satisfying joy left to
us in an age so limited and vulgar as our own, an age grossly carnal in its
pleasures, and grossly common in its aims....
He was a marvelous type, too, this lad, whom by so curious a chance he had met
in Basil’s studio, or could be fashioned into a marvelous type, at any rate. Grace
was his, and the white purity of boyhood, and beauty such as old Greek marbles
kept for us. There was nothing that one could not do with him. He could be made a
Titan or a toy. What a pity it was that such beauty
was destined to fade! And Basil? From a psychological point of view, how
interesting he was! The new manner in art, the fresh mode of looking at life,
suggested so strangely by the merely visible presence of one who was
unconscious of it all; the silent spirit that dwelt in dim woodland, and walked
unseen in open field, suddenly showing herself dad likee and not afraid, because
in his soul who sought for her there had been wakened that wonderful vision to
which alone wonderful things revealed; the mere shapes and patterns of things
becoming, as it were, refined, and gaining a kind of symbolical value, as though
they were themselves patterns of some other and more perfect form whose shadow
they made real: how strange it all was! He remembered something like it in
history. Was it not Plato, that artist in thought, who had first analyzed it? Was it
not bua Roti who had carved it in the colored marble of a Sonet
sequence But in our own century it was strange.... Yes; he would try to be to Dorian
Gray what, without knowing it, the lad was to the painter who had fashioned the wonderful
portrait. He would seek to dominate him— —had already, indeed, half done so. He would
make that wonderful spirit his own. There was something fascinating in
this son of love and death. Suddenly he stopped and glanced up at the house
He found that he had passed his aunt some distance, and, smiling to himself,
turned back. When he entered the somewhat somber hall, the butler told him that
they had gone into lunch. He gave one of the footmen his hat and stick and passed
into the dining room Late as usual, Harry,” cried his aunt, shaking her head at
him. He invented a fasile excuse, and having taken the vacant seat next to her,
looked around to see who was there.
Dorian bowed to him shyly from the end of the table, a flush of pleasure stealing into his
cheek. Opposite was the Duchess of Harley, a lady of admirable good nature and good
temper, much liked by everyone who knew her, and of those ample architectural
proportions that in women who are not duchesses are described by contemporary historians as
stoutness. Next to her sat, on her right, Sir Thomas Burton a Radical member of
Parliament, who followed his leader in public life and in private life followed
the best cooks, dining with the Tories and thinking with the Liberals, in
accordance with a wise and well-known rule. The post on her left was occupied
by Mr D erskin of tradley an old gentleman of considerable charm and
culture, who had fallen, however, into bad habits of silence, having, as he explained
once to Lady Agatha, said everything that he had to say before he was 30
His own neighbor was Mrs vanandel one of his aunt’s oldest friends, a perfect
saint amongst women, but so dreadfully dowy that she reminded one of a badly
bound hym book Fortunately for him she had on the other side Lord forell a most
intelligent middle-aged mediocrity, as bold as a ministerial statement in the
House of Commons, with whom she was conversing in that intensely earnest
manner which is the one unpardonable error, as he remarked once himself,
that all really good people fall into, and from which none of them ever quite
escape. “We are talking about poor dartmore Lord Henry,” cried the duchess,
nodding pleasantly to him across the table. “Do you think he will really marry
this fascinating young person?” “I believe she has made up her mind to propose to him,
Duchess.” “How dreadful!” exclaimed Lady Agatha. “Really someone should
interfere.” “I am told, on excellent authority, that her father keeps an
American dry goods store,” said Sir Thomas Burton looking supercilious. “My uncle has already
suggested pork packing Sir Thomas Dry Goods What are American Dry Goods asked
the duchess, raising her large hands in wonder and accentuating the verb.
“American novels,” answered Lord Henry, helping himself to some quail. The
duchess looked puzzled. “Don’t mind him, my dear,” whispered Lady Agatha. “He never
means means anything that he says.” “When America was discovered,” said
the Radical member— —and he began to give some wearisome facts. Like all people who
try to exhaust a subject, he exhausted his listeners. The duchess sighed and
exercised her privilege of interruption. “I wish to goodness it never
had been discovered at all!” she exclaimed.
“Really, our girls have no chance nowadays.
It is most unfair.” “Perhaps, after all, America never has been discovered,” said Mr erskin I
myself would say that it had merely been detected.” “Oh! but I have seen specimens of
the inhabitants,” answered the duchess vaguely. “I must confess that most of them
are extremely pretty. And they dress well, too. They get all their dresses in Paris.
I wish I could afford to do the same.” “They say that when good Americans die
they go to Paris,” chuckled S Thomas, who had a large wardrobe of human cast off
clothes. “Really! And where do bad Americans go to when they die?” inquired the
duchess. “They go to America,” murmured Lord Henry. Sir Thomas frowned I'm afraid that
your nephew is prejudiced against that great country,” he said to Lady Agatha. “I
have traveled all over it in cars provided by the directors, who, in such matters, are
extremely civil. I assure you that it is an education to visit it.” “But must we
really see Chicago in order to be educated?” asked Mr ersin plaintively. “I
don’t feel up to the journey.” Sir Thomas waved his hand. “Mr
urkin of tradley has the world on his shelves. We practical men like to see
things, not to read about them. The Americans are an extremely interesting
people. They are absolutely reasonable. I think that is their distinguishing
characteristic. Yes, Mr kkin an absolutely reasonable people. I assure you there is
no nonsense about the Americans.” “How dreadful!” cried Lord Henry.
“I can stand brute force, but brute reason is quite unbearable. There is something unfair
about its use. It is hitting below the intellect.” “I do not understand you,” said
Sir Thomas, growing rather red. “I do, Lord Henry,” murmured Mr kkin with a smile.
“Paradoxes are all very well in their way....” rejoined the baronet. “Was that a a
paradox?” asked Mr urin I did not think so.
Perhaps it was. Well, the way of paradoxes is the way of truth. To test reality we
must see it on the tight RPP When the varities become acrobats, we can judge
them.” “Dear me!” said Lady Agatha, “how you men argue I'm sure I never can make out
what you are talking about. Oh! Harry I'm quite vexed with you.
Why do you try to persuade our nice Mr.
Dorian Gray to give up the East End? I assure you he would be quite invaluable.
They would love his playing.” “I want him to play to me,” cried
Lord Henry, smiling, and he looked down the table and caught a bright answering
glance. “But they are so unhappy in White Chapel continued Lady
Agatha. “I can sympathize with everything except suffering,” said Lord Henry,
shrugging his shoulders. “I cannot sympathize with that. It is too ugly, too horrible, too
distressing. There is something terribly morbid in the modern sympathy with pain.
One should sympathize with the color the beauty, the joy of life. The less said
about life SS the better.” “Still, the East End is a very
important problem,” remarked Sir Thomas with a grave shake of the head. “Quite so,”
answered the young lord. “It is the problem of slavery, and we try to solve
it by amusing the slaves.” The politician looked at him keenly.
“What change do you propose, then?” he asked. Lord Henry laughed. “I don’t desire
to change anything in England except the weather,” he answered I'm quite content
with philosophic contemplation. But, as the 19th century has gone bankrupt through an overexp
indit of sympathy, I would suggest that we should appeal to science to put us straight. The
advantage of the emotions is that they lead us astray, and the advantage of
science is that it is not emotional.” “But we have such grave
responsibilities,” ventured Mrs vandela timidly. “Terribly grave,” echoed Lady
Agatha. Lord Henry looked over at Mr kkin Humanity takes itself too seriously.
It is the world’s original sin. If the caveman had known how to laugh, history
would have been different.” “You are really very comforting wobbled the
duchess. “I always felt rather guilty when I came to see your dear aunt, for I take
no interest at all in the East End. For the future I shall be able to look her
in the face without a blush.” “A blush is very becoming, Duchess,” remarked Lord
Henry. “Only when one is young,” she answered. “When an old woman like myself
blushes, it is a very bad sign. Ah! Lord Henry, I wish you would tell
me how to become young again.” He thought for a moment.
“Can you remember any great error that you committed in your early days, Duchess?”
he asked, looking at her across the table.
“A great many, I fear,” she cried. “Then commit them over again,” he said gravely.
“To get back one’s youth, one has merely to repeat one’s folies A delightful
theory!” she exclaimed. “I must put it into practice.” “A dangerous theory!” came from s
Thomas’s tight lips. Lady Agatha shook her head, but could not help being amused.
Mr kkin listened. “Yes,” he continued, “that is one of the great secrets of
life. Nowadays most people die of a sort of creeping common sense, and discover
when it is too late that the only things one never regrets are one’s
mistakes.” A laugh ran around the table. He played with the idea and grew
willful tossed it into the air and transformed it; let it escape and recaptured it;
made it iridescent with fancy and winged it with paradox. The praise of folly, as
he went on, soared into a philosophy, and philosophy herself became young, and
catching the mad music of pleasure, wearing, one might fancy, her win stained
robe and wreath of ivy, danced like a bante over the hills of life, and mocked
the slow Silenus for being sober. Facts fled before her like frightened forest things.
Her white feet trod the huge press at which wise Omar sits, till the seething
grape juice rose around her bare limbs in waves of purple bubbles, or crawled in
red foam over the vat’s black, dripping, sloping sides. It was an extraordinary
improvisation. He felt that the eyes of Dorian Gray were fixed on him, and the
consciousness that amongst his audience there was one whose temperament he
wished to fascinate seemed to give his wit Keen and to lend color to his
imagination. He was brilliant, fantastic, irresponsible. He charmed his listeners
out of themselves, and they followed his pipe, laughing. Dorian Gray never took his
gaze off him, but sat like one under a spell, smiles chasing each other over his
lips and wonder growing grave in his darkening eyes. At last, liveried in the costume of
the age, reality entered the room in the shape of a servant to tell the duchess that her
carriage was waiting. She rung her hands in mock despair. “How annoying!” she cried. “I must go.
I have to call for my husband at the club, to take him to some absurd meeting
at Willis’s Rooms, where he is going to
be in the chair. If I'm late he is sure
to be furious, and I couldn’t have a scene in this bonnet. It is far too
fragile. A harsh word would ruin it.
No, I must go, dear Agatha goodbye Lord Henry, you are quite delightful and dreadfully
demoralizing I'm sure I don’t know what to say about your views. You must come
and dine with us some night.
Tuesday? Are you disengaged Tuesday?” “For you I would throw over
anybody, Duchess,” said Lord Henry with a bow. “Ah! that is very nice, and very wrong
of you,” she cried; “so mind you come”; and she swept out of the room, followed by
Lady Agatha and the other ladies. When Lord Henry had sat down
again, Mr kkin moved round, and taking a chair close to him, placed his hand upon
his arm. “You talk books away,” he said; “why
don’t you write one?” “I am too fond of reading books to care to write them, Mr
kkin I should like to write a novel certainly, a novel that would be as
lovely as a Persian carpet and as unreal.
But there is no literary public in England for anything except newspapers primas and
encyclopedias Of all people in the world the English have the least sense of the beauty of
literature.” “I fear you are right,” answered Mr kkin I myself used to have literary
ambitions, but I gave them up long ago.
And now, my dear young friend, if you will
allow me to call you so, may I ask if you
really meant all that you said to us at lunch?” “I quite forget what I said,” smiled
Lord Henry Henry Was it all very bad?” “Very bad indeed. In fact I consider
you extremely dangerous, and if anything happens to our good duchess, we shall all
look on you as being primarily responsible. But I should like to talk to
you about life. The generation into which I was born was tedious someday when you are tired of
London, come down to tradley and expound to me your philosophy of pleasure over
some admirable Burgundy I am fortunate enough to possess.” “I shall be charmed. A visit to
tradley would be a great privilege. It has a perfect host, and a perfect
library.” “You will complete it,” answered the old gentleman with a courteous bow.
“And now I must bid goodbye to your excellent aunt. I am due at the
aanam It is the hour when we sleep there.” “All of you, Mr
kkin 40 of us, in 40 armchairs We are prac ing for an English Academy of
Letters.” Lord Henry laughed and rose I'm going to the park,” he
cried. As he was passing out of the door, Dorian Gray touched him on the
arm. “Let me come with you,” he murmured. “But I thought you had promised Basil
hallwood to go and see him,” answered Lord Henry. “I would sooner come with you; yes, I
feel I must come with you. Do let me. And
you will promise to talk to me all the time? No one talks so wonderfully as you
do.” “Ah I've talked quite enough for today said Lord Henry, smiling. “All I want now
is to look at life. You may come and look at it with me, if you care
to.” CHAPTER